In this slide, we will explore the core
departments that define major tech companies.
These departments include Ads Monetization, AI/ML Platforms, Cloud Infrastructure,
and Growth, which are crucial for revenue and innovation.
Each company, such as Google, Amazon, Microsoft, and Apple,
places varying emphasis on these departments based on their business models.
For instance, Google focuses heavily on Ads and AI,
while Amazon prioritizes its AWS and Marketplace.
Let's delve into how Ads Monetization serves
as a critical revenue driver for tech companies.
Departments focused on Ads are pivotal as they directly generate revenue,
especially for companies like Google and Meta.
For example, Google Services revenue growth
is largely driven by Search and YouTube ads,
which alone generated over $60 billion annually.
Similarly, Amazon's advertising business has
become a major profit source alongside AWS,
which reported $14.2 billion in operating income in Q1 2026.
Now, let's examine the role of recommendation algorithms in tech companies.
These systems are crucial as they dictate what users see and interact with,
directly impacting engagement and revenue.
For instance, TikTok's recommendation system is central to its user experience,
while Netflix and Amazon also rely heavily on
personalized recommendations to drive subscriptions and sales.
The technical complexity of these algorithms makes them one of
the most strategically important areas within these companies.
Next, let's discuss the concept of Growth within major tech companies.
Unlike traditional marketing, Growth encompasses data analysis, experimentation,
and user lifecycle management to optimize user engagement.
This includes strategies for user acquisition, retention, and conversion,
which are essential for long-term success.
Companies like Meta, TikTok,
and Amazon have established dedicated Growth teams to focus on these critical areas.
Let's explore the significance of core product teams within tech companies.
While all product teams contribute, only a few are deemed core,
as they control critical user entry points and revenue streams.
For example, Google’s Search and YouTube, Amazon’s Marketplace,
and Apple’s iOS are essential for their respective companies' success.
These core product lines typically receive high attention
from executives due to their direct impact on company valuation.
Now, let's look at the foundational role of Cloud and Infrastructure departments.
In today's AI-driven landscape,
these departments have become essential for scalability and performance,
with Microsoft Azure and AWS leading the charge.
For instance, Microsoft reported Azure revenue exceeding $75 billion in 2025,
highlighting its importance as a growth engine.
Similarly, Nvidia's Data Center revenue reached $75.2 billion,
showcasing the increasing demand for AI infrastructure.
Next, we will discuss the evolution of AI/ML platforms within tech companies.
AI/ML departments have transitioned from purely
research-focused to core production units that address business needs.
Key areas include large language models, ads models, and AI safety protocols,
which are crucial for operational success.
Companies like Google and Microsoft are heavily investing in these areas,
reflecting their growing importance in the tech landscape.
Let's explore the critical role of data and experimentation in tech companies.
These departments serve as decision-making centers,
guiding product strategies based on data-driven insights.
Tech companies rely on methods like A/B testing and
causal analysis to inform their product decisions,
ensuring they are backed by solid evidence.
Roles such as Data Scientists and Engineers are vital in these departments,
particularly in Ads, Growth, and Product teams.
Now, let's discuss the increasing importance of trust, safety,
and privacy departments.
These functions have evolved from support roles to
essential departments that ensure compliance and user safety.
They focus on areas like advertising privacy, content moderation,
and account security, which are critical for sustaining operations.
Companies such as Meta, Google,
and Apple are heavily investing in these areas to mitigate regulatory pressures.
Next, let's examine the role of marketplace
and commerce departments in tech companies.
These departments are particularly vital for companies like Amazon and Apple,
as they encompass logistics, payments, and fulfillment.
For Amazon, the Marketplace is not just an e-commerce platform but
a comprehensive system that integrates various services.
Apple's Services revenue has also reached record highs,
showcasing the importance of this sector beyond hardware sales.
Now, let's discuss the significance of developer ecosystems in major tech companies.
These platforms are not just about immediate revenue;
they create long-term competitive advantages by locking in developers.
For instance, Microsoft’s Azure and Google Cloud provide extensive
tools and resources to foster developer engagement.
Nvidia exemplifies this by building a strong
moat through its CUDA platform and AI libraries,
which enhance its market position.
Finally, let's look at the ranking of core departments in major tech companies.
The most critical departments, or Tier 1, include Ads Monetization,
Recommendation Systems, Core Product, and Cloud Infrastructure.
Tier 2 departments, while important, may not be the top priority for every company,
including Growth and Data Science.
Lastly, Tier 3 departments, such as Enterprise Sales and HR,
are essential but typically not part of the technical core.
Let's take a closer look at the core departments specific to major tech companies.
For Google, the most core departments include Search, Ads, YouTube, and Cloud,
which drive both revenue and user engagement.
Amazon's core departments encompass AWS, Marketplace, Logistics, and Ads,
reflecting its diverse business model.
Apple's core includes the iPhone, Services, Ecosystem, and Privacy,
showcasing its integrated approach to hardware and software.